Guide to the Collection of Original Artwork for Bookplate Designs
Yale University Arts Library
Collection of original artwork for bookplate designs
1852-1933
1920-1930
BKP 131
Yale University Arts Library
0.25
(1 box)
This is an artificial collection of original artwork for bookplates--also known as ex-libris. Multiple artists are represented.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials acquired by purchase.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This is an artificial collection of original artwork for bookplates--also known as ex-libris. Multiple artists are represented.
Arrangement
Arranged by date of acquisition.
Bookplates -- Specimens.; Bookplates; Drawings (visual works); Stauffer, David McNeely, 1845-1913; Emerson, Edith, 1888-1965; Mayhew, Horace, 1816-1872
- Box listing
  - I am but a gatherer and disposer of other men's stuff., 1898; 1 drawing: black and white; 35 x 28 cm (Box 1)
    Custodial History
    Acquired by purchase, 2012-02.
    Related Archival Materials note
    BKP 30, Box 106, Folder 3185.
    Scope and Contents
    This is a pen-and-ink drawing, signed and dated by the artist, David McNeely Stauffer. This design was used for the bookplate of William Livermore Kingman (see related materials in BKP 30).
  - Design for the bookplate of Lydia Rowland Woolman., 1933; 1 drawing: black and white; 14.5 x 21 in (Box 1)
    BKP 30, Box 190, Folder 4677.
    This is a pencil and charcoal drawing, signed by the artist, Edith Emerson. The design was used for the bookplate of Lydia Rowland Woolman (see related materials in BKP 30).
  - Design for the bookplate of John and Katherine Knight., [1929]; 1 drawing: black and white; 18.5 x 12.7 cm, on board 30.3 x 20.4 cm; 1 print: black and white; 9 x 6.3 cm, on paper 15.7 x 12 cm (Box 1)
    Acquired by purchase, 2012-11.
    This is an ink drawing on board by C. W. Franc, signed with a monogram and the date. Also included is the resulting bookplate, reduced to half the size of the drawing and printed from a zinc plate.
  - Pour y parvenir., 1852; 1 drawing: ink and watercolor; 7 x 6.25 in (Box 1)
    This is an ink and watercolor drawing for the bookplate of Horace Mayhew.
  - Design for the bookplate of E. Getmanskii., 1948; 1 drawing: ink; 19 x 13 cm; 1 bookplate; 8.8 x 6.9 cm (Box 1)
    Acquired by purchase, 2013-01.
    This is an ink drawing by Igor Filipchenko for a Leniniana bookplate of E. Getmanskii. Also included is the resulting bookplate with the artist's stamp on the verso.
  - Design for the bookplate of E. Smirnov., undated; 1 drawing: ink; 19 x 13 cm; 1 bookplate; 9.2 x 7 cm (Box 1)
    This is an ink drawing by Igor Filipchenko for the bookplate of E. Smirnov. Also included is the resulting bookplate with the artist's stamp on the verso.
  - Design for the bookplate of E. P. Garin., 1980; 1 sheet with several drawings: ink and pencil; 18.9 x 27 cm; 1 bookplate; 8.9 x 6.8 cm; 1 newspaper clipping (Box 1)
    This is a sheet with several ink and pencil sketches by Igor Filipchenko for the bookplate of Ėrast Pavlovich Garin (1902-1980), who was a comic actor in Soviet film and theater. Also included are the resulting bookplate (signed by the artist in pencil) and a 1983 Russian newspaper clipping about how films and actors inspire ex-libris designs (according to bookseller's description).
  - Design for the bookplate of the Memorial Museum., undated; 2 drawings on 1 sheet: ink; 12.4 x 15.3 cm; 1 bookplate; 8.8 x 6.9 cm; 1 newspaper clipping (Box 1)
    This is a sheet with two drawings in ink by Igor Filipchenko for the bookplate of the Memorial Museum. The design depicts Basil (Vasilii Vasil'evich) Porik (1920-1944), a lieutenant in the Soviet Army who was active in the resistance movement in France during World War II and later named a hero of the Soviet Union. Also included are the resulting bookplate (with the artist's stamp on the verso) and a 1985 Russian newspaper clipping about an ex-libris exhibition held at Bookshop No. 14 in Vinnytsya, Ukraine, and dedicated to the 40th anniversary of the Great Patriotic War (according to bookseller's description).
  - Design for the bookplate of Ranier M. Rilke., undated; 1 drawing: ink and crayon; 14.3 x 10.7 cm (Box 1)
    Acquired by purchase, 2013-09.
    This design is an example of an "imaginary bookplate." Rather than referring to mythical or fantastic subject matter, an imaginary bookplate is an artist's conception of a personal ex-libris design without consent or even contact with the designated patron. Artists often create imaginary bookplates for famous individuals, such as writers, politicians, celebrities, etc.
    Artist's monogram possibly H. J.
  - Design for the bookplate of James Ogilvie Grant, Earl of Seafield & Chief of Clan Grant., circa 1920; 1 drawing: ink; 26.4 x 18.7 cm (Box 1)
    This is a drawing by John R. Sutherland.
  - Design for the Chester C. Corbin Public Library bookplate in memory of Mary Irene Marble, 1876-1925., 1930; 1 drawing: ink; 28.6 x 20.3 cm (Box 1)
    This is a drawing by F. C. Blank.
  - Preliminary sketch for the Chester C. Corbin Public Library bookplate in memory of Mary Irene Marble, 1876-1925., [1930]; 1 drawing: pencil; 12.4 x 7.4 cm, on mount 12.6. x 7.5 cm (Box 1)
  - Preliminary sketch for the Chester C. Corbin Public Library bookplate in memory of Mary Irene Marble, 1876-1925., [1930]; 1 drawing: pencil; 12.3 x 7.2 cm, on mount 12.6 x 7.5 cm (Box 1)
  - Design for the bookplate of Forrest Bennetts., [circa 1930s-1940s]; 1 drawing: ink; 31.2 x 20.3 cm (Box 1)
    Acquired by purchase, 2014-01.
    This is a drawing by William O. Fitzgerald.
  - Design for the bookplate of Dr. Lucian Pfleger., 1907; 1 drawing: ink; 30.8 x 29 cm (Box 1)
    Acquired by purchase, 2014-04.
    This is a drawing by Eug[en] Moßgraber.
  - Designs for the bookplate of Clare Talbot., undated; 6 drawings on 1 sheet: ink; 9.2 x 15.4 cm (Box 1)
    The sheet contains six preliminary ink drawings on card stock by Carl S. Junge for the bookplate collector and writer Clare Ryan Talbot.
  - Design for the bookplate of Helen Schurig., undated; 1 drawing: pencil; 16.3 x 10.8 cm; 1 bookplate; 9.5 x 5 cm (Box 1)
    In addition to the original pencil drawing by Carl S. Junge, the finished, color-printed bookplate is also included.
  - Design for the bookplate of Edna Voguild., undated; 1 drawing: pencil; 20.3 x 12.6 cm; 1 bookplate; 12.7 x 9.7 cm (Box 1)
    In addition to the original pencil drawing by Carl S. Junge, the finished bookplate is also included.
  - Designs for the title page of book on "Bookplates by Carl S. Junge.", 1940 undated; 1 drawing: pencil and paint; 26.5 x 18 cm; 1 drawing: pencil; 22.6 x 16.8 cm (Box 1)
    Includes two preliminary pencil drawings on paper by Carl S. Junge for title pages of books about Junge's own bookplates.